Guide to the Cathryn Irvis Papers, 1978-1980 AIS.2006.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Cathryn Irvis Papers
1978-1980
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Irvis, Cathryn
AIS.2006.02
6.25 Linear Feet (13 boxes)
The papers of Cathryn Irvis, a local advocate of health and children's rights, are heavily focused on the United Nation's International Year of the Child (1979). Information about planning and organizing the conference at the state and regional levels are demonstrated through Irvis' role as chairperson of the Pennsylvania Committee for the International Year of the Child. This collection documents activities and projects and includes correspondence, programs, and pamphlets. A small amount of material about Irvis' interests, arranged as subject files, include African American and minority organizations, health care, education, the arts and politics.
Biography
Cathryn (Cathy) Irvis was born in Athens, Georgia, on April 7, 1934. She attended the National School of Nursing in Chicago and was on the Board of Directors of the American Diabetes Association. She was married to the late civil rights leader and former Pennsylvania House Speaker K. Leroy Irvis. Like her husband, she was concerned with bettering the community and served on several committees in western Pennsylvania, including Black Women in Health, the Review Committee for the United Way of Allegheny County, Women in Urban Crisis, Inc., the Governor's Council on the Arts, and the Pittsburgh Opportunities Industrialization Center Auxiliary. As co-chair of the Pennsylvania Committee for the International Year of the Child (1979), Mrs. Irvis was involved with many children's concerns, particularly health issues.
In 1978, Pa. Governor Milton Shapp appointed Mrs. Irvis chairperson of the Pennsylvania Committee for the International Year of the Child (IYC). She invited doctors, social workers, professors, and other specialists on children's concerns in Pennsylvania to participate in the planning of IYC studies and activities which would both celebrate children and address the issues most critical to them. Education and health were especially important, and many of the materials cover school lunch programs, nutrition, teen pregnancy, and early childhood special education.
Mrs. Irvis was later joined by co-chairperson Malcom Lazin and Honorary chairperson Ginny Thornburgh and shifted her focus to the IYC Western Pennsylvania Sub-Committee. Over the course of the year, the committee identified possible troubles in the region and prepared a survey on drug abuse, handicaps, school teachers, emotional concerns, and other topics. The data and evaluation was presented in "Assessment of the Current Health and Educational Status and Needs of Children in Western Pennsylvania", which was presented to Mrs. Irvis in 1980.
Mrs. Irvis was also associated with IYC-Pittsburgh, which planned a Read-A-Thon at the Carnegie Public Library, a fashion show, an art show, workshops on teen pregnancy and teenage parenting, and a children's festival, among other events. The materials include background on IYC and its committees as well as information on some children's issues addressed by the event.
Scope and Content Notes
The bulk of the Cathryn Irvis Papers pertain to her activities as co-chair of the Pennsylvania Committee for the International Year of the Child (IYC). The United Nations (UN) designated 1979 as The International Year of the Child, and coordinated activities, workshops, and events around the many issues faced by children worldwide. The IYC (1979) marked the 20th anniversary of the UN's Declaration of the Rights of the Child and was organized and overseen by UNICEF. In the United States, IYC became the incentive for programs ranging from young children's festivals and art shows in individual towns to changes in legislation and the creation of new child welfare groups.
Folders 16-32 contain pamphlets and correspondence relating to some of Mrs. Irvis' other activities. These activities and interests are arranged as subject files and include information on the health field, the arts, organizations focused on African Americans and other minorities, education, and politics. Although political matter is limited in this collection, there are some materials relating to K. Leroy Irvis' campaign for Pittsburgh City Council and Pennsylvania State Representative for the 19th District. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Cathryn Irvis on May 5, 2006.
Previous Citation
Cathryn Irvis Papers, 1978-1980, AIS.2006.02, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Further information on Cathryn Irvis may be found in the following additions of the K. Leroy Irvis Papers, 1865-2007, AIS.1971.06, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System:
Series IV. 1995 Addition, Subseries 7. Mrs. Cathryn Irvis and Subseries 18. Photographs
Series VII. 2010 Addition, Subseries 4. Cathryn Irvis (Cathy) and Subseries 19. Photographs
Personal papers; Women; Pennsylvania; Education; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Campaign paraphernalia; Career education; Nutrition; Health; Early childhood special education; Teenage pregnancy; Family violence; International Year of the Child, 1979 -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; International Year of the Child, 1979 -- Pennsylvania; UNICEF; United Nations; United Way of Allegheny County (Pa.); American Diabetes Association; Irvis, Cathryn; Opportunities Industrialization Center (Pittsburgh, Pa.). Auxiliary
- Agendas (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Background Information (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Benefit Concert Material (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Biographical Information (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Budget, December 1, 1978- January 30,1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Cathy's IYC Schedule (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Child Safety (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Children's Books- Letty Shaw (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Children's Exposition (Box 1, Folder 9)
- City IYC Chair Persons (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Commission on Higher Education (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Committee Members' Appointment Letters (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Commonwealth Child Development Committee (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Comprehensive Employment and Training Act (CETA) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Contacts (Organizations) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Contributions (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Convocations Contact Persons (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Convocation Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Incoming Correspondence, August-September 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Incoming Correspondence, October-November 1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Outgoing Correspondence, October-November 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Incoming Correspondence, December 1978-January 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Outgoing Correspondence, December 1978-January 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Incoming Correspondence, February-March 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Outgoing Correspondence, February-March 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Incoming Correspondence, April-May 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Outgoing Correspondence, April-May 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Incoming Correspondence, June-July 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Incoming Correspondence, August-September 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Outgoing Correspondence, August-September 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Incoming Correspondence, November-December 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Outgoing Correspondence, November-December 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Incoming Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence with Honorary Members (Box 2, Folder 13)
- County Commissioners' Proclamation (IYC) (Box 2, Folder 14)
- County of Allegheny (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Donations (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Easter Egg Hunt (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Expense Vouchers (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Fell Spalding, Goff and Rubin (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Film Information (Box 2, Folder 20)
- General Information (IYC) (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Governor's Proclamation (IYC) (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Gov.'s Task Force (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Grandmother of the Year (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Health Screening (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Hershey Park Expo (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Hill House Association (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Honorary Members (Box 3, Folder 8)
- House of Representatives Commonwealth of Pennsylvania (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Hunger for Action Coalition (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Invitations (Box 3, Folder 11)
- International Year of the Child- Bank Statements (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Imaginarium (Box 3, Folder 13)
- IYC (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
- IYC (Box 4, Folder 1)
- IYC (I), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- IYC (II), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- IYC Report, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- IYC Report, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- IYC Activities (Box 4, Folder 6)
- IYC Committee Activities (Box 5, Folder 1)
- IYC Committee Members (Box 5, Folder 2)
- IYC Erie County (Box 5, Folder 3)
- IYC Greater Pittsburgh (Box 5, Folder 4)
- IYC Health Program (Box 5, Folder 5)
- IYC Letters (Box 5, Folder 6)
- IYC Meeting Notes and Planning (Box 5, Folder 7)
- IYC Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 8)
- IYC Pittsburgh Area Events (Box 5, Folder 9)
- IYC Posters (Map-case 16, Drawer 12)
- IYC Proposal (Box 5, Folder 10)
- IYC Staff Job Descriptions (Box 5, Folder 11)
- IYC State Coordinators (Box 5, Folder 12)
- IYC Task Force (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Kidfest Information (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Kingsley House Association (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Legislation (Box 5, Folder 16)
- March of Dimes-1 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- March of Dimes-2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Maryland IYC (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Materials from the National Arts and the Handicapped Information Service (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Meetings Notices (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Minutes (Box 6, Folder 5)
- NAACP (Box 6, Folder 6)
- National Commission Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 7)
- National Council of Negro Women (Box 6, Folder 8)
- National Endowment for Children's Television Act, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Needs Assessment Survey (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Newsletter- Cathryn Irvis (Box 6, Folder 12)
- PA Association for Retarded Citizens, Inc. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- PA Association of Tobacco and Candy Distributors, Inc. (Box 6, Folder 14)
- PA College of Optometry (Box 6, Folder 15)
- PA Council on the Arts-1 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- PA Council on the Arts-2 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- PA IYC Articles for Newsletters (Box 7, Folder 1)
- PA IYC Newsletters (Box 7, Folder 2)
- PA Neighborhood Assistance (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Pamphlets- IYC (Box 7, Folder 4-9)
- Pamphlets- Supporting Information (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
- Pamphlets- Supporting Information (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
- People Gas (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Philadelphia Committee IYC, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Presidents Speech (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Press Conference IYC, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Press Releases (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Proposal (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Puppets- Any Buddy Pupplets (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Region III Coordinators (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Reports (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Responses to Letters Sent to Organizations, April 18, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Resolutions (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Rough Drafts- Letters, News Releases, etc. (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Senior Citizens Workshop (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Speak up for Children (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Speaking Engagements (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Special Letters (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Special Projects- IYC (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Status Report (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Three Rivers Youth Board of Directors (Box 11, Folder 3)
- UN National Commission on IYC (Box 11, Folder 4)
- United Nations General Assembly (Box 11, Folder 5)
- United Way of Allegheny County (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
- University and City Ministries (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Upcoming Events (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Valley Child Care Center (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Variety Club of Pittsburgh (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic-1 (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic-2 (Box 11, Folder 13)
- White House Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Women in Urban Crisis Inc. (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Workshops (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Youth in the Performing Arts (Box 12, Folder 4)
- African American Organizations and Events-1 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- African American Organizations and Events-2 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- American Diabetes Association (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Arts and Performance (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Black Women's Crusade (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Campaigns (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Education (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Ethnic and Minority Organizations and Issues (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Humanitarian Organizations (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Memorandum - Needs of the Elderly (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Opportunities Industrialization Center (OIC) Auxiliary (Box 13, Folder 2)
- OIC Auxiliary (Box 13, Folder 3)
- OIC Auxiliary File (Box 13, Folder 4)
- OIC Board of Directors-1 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- OIC Board of Directors-2 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Political Information (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Religious Organizations (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Sister Cities International (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Women's Organizations and Events (Box 13, Folder 10)